Guide to the Adnan Pachachi book collection AD.MC.085
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
Adnan Pachachi book collection
1911-2014
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
Pachachi, Adnan, 1923-2019
AD.MC.085
46 Volumes
Consists of selected books and other publications from the personal library of Adnan al-Pachachi (1923-2019), an Iraqi politician and diplomat who also served as an adviser to the government of the United Arab Emirates. Collection includes titles inscribed to Pachachi from their authors, usually pertaining to the history and current affairs of Iraq or the United Arab Emirates, or titles otherwise related to the life and career of Pachachi and his family.
Conditions governing access
Collection is open for use in the Archives and Special Collections Reading Room, New York University Abu Dhabi Library.
Immediate source of acquisition
Collection donated by the Estate of Adnan Pachachi, October 2020.
Arrangement
Titles are arranged in three categories: Iraq, United Arab Emirates, and General. Within those categories, they are alphabetized by author.
Biographical note
Adnan al-Pachachi was born in 14 May 1923 in Baghdad, into a politically active Sunni family. His father, Muzahim Amin al-Pachachi, served as Prime Minister of Iraq in 1948-1949, his uncle Hamdi al-Pachachi served as both Prime Minister (1944-1946) and Foreign Minister (1948) of Iraq; and his cousin Nadim al-Pachachi served as Secretary-General of OPEC (1971-1972).
Pachachi was educated at Victoria College, Alexandria, where he was initially drawn to Arab nationalist political movements; and received a degree in political science from American University in Beirut in 1943. From 1950-1958 he served in the Political Department of the Iraqi Ministry of Foreign Affairs, but was removed due to his support of Egyptian nationalist leader Gamel Abdel Nasser. Following the 1958 revolution in Iraq, he was appointed by the Qassim regime to serve as the Permanent Representative of Iraq to the United Nations in 1959, a post in which he served for much of the next decade. During this period, he also served from 1965-1967 as Foreign Minister of Iraq, during which time he was vocal in his support of Palestinian rights and his opposition to Israel during the Six-Day War in 1967.
Following the coup that brought Saddam Hussein to power in Iraq, Pachachi went into exile in 1969, moving to the Emirate of Abu Dhabi, and began serving as a counselor to the Emirate's leader, Sheikh Zayed bin Sultan al-Nahyan, who appointed him a Minister of State in July 1971. Following the formation of the United Arab Emirates in December 1971, Pachachi played a key role in paving the way for the new country's admittance to the United Nations.
After the U.S. invasion of Iraq and overthrow of Saddam Hussein in 2003, Pachachi returned to Iraq, initially to serve in the Iraq Governing Council, where he was a vocal critic of the U.S. actions and policies within the country. In 2005 he participated in the first legislative elections, heading the Assembly of Independent Democrats, and subsequently served in the National Assembly. In 2010, he stood as a candidate again with Ayad Allawi's Iraqi List, but by 2011 had grown increasingly pessimistic about the chances for a secular democracy in Iraq, and returned to Abu Dhabi.
Adnan Pachachi died in Abu Dhabi at the age of 96 on 17 November 2019.
[source: Wikipedia article, "Adnan Pachachi," https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adnan_Pachachi, accessed 13 May 2021].
Content Description
The Adnan Pachachi collection consists of selected books and other publications from the personal library of Adnan al-Pachachi (1923-2019), former Iraqi foreign minister and adviser to the government of the United Arab Emirates. The collection includes titles inscribed to Pachachi from their authors, usually pertaining to the history and current affairs of Iraq or the United Arab Emirates, or titles otherwise related to the life and career of Pachachi and his family.
The books in this collection were selected from the library in his home in Abu Dhabi. Selections were made on the basis of subject matter of the titles, and in particular how these titles appeared to have related to Pachachi's own lived experience, both as a political figure from Iraq, as well as his role as a long-time resident of Abu Dhabi and adviser to the rulers of that Emirate, and of the United Arab Emirates.
A substantial portion of this collection consist of presentation copies inscribed to Pachachi from their authors. Many of these consist of memoirs, historical works, literary titles, and works on current affairs and politics, mostly from Iraqi authors and pertaining to Iraq. Additional works about the history and culture of the United Arab Emirates, and in particular, Abu Dhabi, are also included, with some of them being presentation copies, others consisting of works that included essays by Pachachi.
An additional group of titles not included in this collection were added to the Main Collection of the NYU Abu Dhabi Library. These consisted of works of general interest, typically about world history or the history of the Middle East, but not otherwise related to Pachachi.
- Iraq titles, 1963-2014
  - ʻAbd al-Wahhāb, ʻAṭā. Al-Amīr Abd'allah: sūrah qalamīyah (Bayrūt: al-Mu assasah al-Dirāsāt wa-al-Nashr, 2001)
    General
    Inscribed by author on flyleaf, to Adnan Pachachi, November 2001. Aleph BSN: 0791281
  - ʻAbd al-Wahhāb, ʻAṭā. ʻAlá hāmish (al-Sulālah): mā qālahu al-kuttāb al-ʻIrāqīyūn ʻan kitāb Sulālat al-ṭīn li-ʻAṭā ʻAbd al-Wahhāb. (Bayrūt: al-Muʼassasah al-ʻArabīyah lil-Dirāsāt wa-al-Nashr, 2009)
    Inscribed by author on flyleaf, to Adnan Pachachi, October 2009. ISBN: 978995336334X. OCLC: 481173868. Aleph BSN: 3270801.
  - ʻAbd al-Wahhāb, ʻAṭā. Sulālat al-ṭīn: sīrat maʼsāh / [Progeny of clay] (Bayrūt: al-Muʼassasah al-ʻArabīyah lil-Dirāsāt wa-al-Nashr, 2004)
    Inscription from author to Adnan Pachachi, on flyleaf, dated March 2005. ISBN: 9953361428, Aleph BSN: 0059516
  - Allawi, Ali A. Iḥtilāl al-ʻIrāq: ribḥ al-ḥarb wa-khasārat al-salām (Bayrūt: al-Muʼassasah al-ʻArabīyah lil-Dirāsāt wa-al-Nashr, 2009)
    Inscribed by author on flyleaf, to Adnan Pachachi, April 2009. ISBN: 9789953362866. OCLC: 551125301. Aleph BSN: 7944557
  - Aʻrajī, Ḥalīm Ḥasan ʻAbd ʻAlī. al-Shaykh Khawwām, 1881-1967: al-thāʼir-- al-insān: qiṣṣat taḥaddī al-tabʻīyah wa-al-taʻassuf fī ẓill ẓurūf al-qahr wa-al-takhalluf (Baghdad, 2002)
    Inscribed by author on flyleaf, to Adnan Pachachi, May 2003. Aleph BSN: 7974418
  - Baḥrānī, Iḥsān Raʼūf. Nabaḍāt al-dhākirah: mudhakkirāt. (Bayrūt: al-Muʼassasah al-ʻArabīyah lil-Dirāsāt wa-al-Nashr, 2011)
    Inscribed by author on flyleaf, to Adnan Pachachi, September 2011. ISBN: 9786144190166. OCLC: 781413262. Aleph BSN: 3520096.
  - Bāqr, Farhān. Hakumī al-ḥakām min qāsim ila Saddām (Sharjah: Safi, 2012)
    Inscribed by author on title page, to Adnan Pachachi, April 2013. Aleph BSN: 7974410
  - Fawzī, Aḥmad. 12 ra'īs wuzarā' fī al-'ahd al-malakī (Baghdād: Yuṭlabu min Maktabat al-Fikr al-ʻArab 1984)
    OCLC: 13423569, Aleph BSN: 2852230.
  - Finnie, David H. Shifting lines in the sand: Kuwait's elusive frontier with Iraq (London: I.B. Tauris, 1992)
    ISBN: 1850435707. OCLC: 28471240. Aleph BSN: 7944544.
  - al-Hāfidh, Mahdī. al-'Irāq: nabū'āt al-āmal (Baghdād: Dār Mīzūbūtamīya, 2013).
    Inscribed by author on flyleaf, to Adnan Pachachi, May 2013. Aleph BSN: 7974113
  - Ḥanẓal, Fāliḥ. Asrār maqtal al-ʻāʼilah al-mālikah fī al-ʻIrāq: awwal ṣafḥah dāmīyah fī tārīkh al-ʻIrāq al-ḥadīth, 14 Tamūz 1958 (London: Dār al-Ḥikmah, 2008).
    Inscribed by author on title page, to Adnan Pachachi, May 2008. ISBN: 1904923534. OCLC: 284636087. Aleph BSN: 7994554
  - Khāliṣ, Maḥmūd. Dhākirat al-waraq: sittūn ʻāman min tārīkh al-ʻIrāq al-ḥadīth fī yawmīyāt Maḥmūd Khāliṣ (Bayrūt: al-Muʼassasah al-ʻArabīyah lil-Dirāsāt wa-al-Nashr, 2010)
    Inscribed by author on flyleaf, to Adnan Pachachi, in Amman, Jordan, September 2010. ISBN: 9789953361053. OCLC: 668111670. Aleph BSN: 3380128.
  - Kirdar, Nemir. In pursuit of fulfilment: my life journey. (London: Weidenfeld & Nicolson, 2012)
    Inscribed by author on title page, to Adnan Pachachi. ISBN: 9780297868606. OCLC: 827726780. Aleph BSN: 7944543.
  - Laperruque, Cosette Marie; Murphy, Mary Alice. Return to Baghdad: an American woman's journey (Baltimore: PublishAmerica, 2003)
    Inscription from authors to Adnan Pachachi, January 2004. ISBN: 1592869777. OCLC: 56190269 Aleph BSN: 7944549.
  - Morris, James [Jan Morris]. al-Mulūk al-Hāshimīyūn (Beirut: Al-maktab al'alami al-talif wa al-tarjimah, n.d. )
    Translation of: James [Jan] Morris. The Hashemite kings. Aleph BSN: 7974417
  - Murūwah, Karīm. Fī al-baḥth ʻan al-mustaqbal: ḥiwār fikrī wa-siyāsī wa-shakhṣī ajratahu al-bāḥithah al-Maghribīyah Maryam Sīdī Ḥaydah (Beirut: Dār al-Sāqī, 2009)
    Inscribed by author on flyleaf, to Adnan Pachachi. ISBN: 9781855163263. OCLC: 302286051. Aleph BSN: 3109406
  - Murūwah, Karīm. Naḥwa nahḍah jadīdah lil-yasār fī al-ālam al-'Arabī (Bayrūt: Dār al-Sāqī, 2010)
    Inscribed by author on flyleaf, to Adnan Pachachi, April 2010. ISBN: 9781855166172. OCLC: 650437834. Aleph BSN: 7944559.
  - Safiḥāt min tārīkh al-'Irāq al-ma'āṣir, 1914-1958: mudhakirāt al farīq awal rukin Sālih Sā'ib al-Jiburī (Beirut: AlMaaref Forum, 2012).
    Inscription to Adnan Pachachi on flyleaf, 2013. ISBN: 9784164280133. OCLC: 875043175. Aleph BSN: 7974411
  - Shikārah, Aḥmad ʻAbd al-Razzāq. al-ʻIrāq: tadāʻīyāt mā baʻda al-intikhābāt al-barlamānīyah wa-qurb al-insiḥāb al-Amrīkī. (Abu Dhabi: Markaz al-Imārāt lil-Dirāsāt wa-al-Buḥūth al-Istirātījīyah, 2011)
    Inscribed by author on title page, to Adnan Pachachi. ISBN: 9789948143888. OCLC: 982119263. Aleph BSN: 7944558
  - Sousa, Ahmed. Fayaḍānāt Baghdād fī al-tārīkh: baḥth fī tārīkh fayaḍānāt anhur al-ʻIrāq wa-taʼthīruhā bi-al-nisbah li-madīnat Baghdād = The floods of Baghdad in history (Baghdād: Al-Adib Press, 1963-1965)
    OCLC: 10803258. Aleph BSN: 3330177.
  - Wardī, ʻAlī. Lamaḥāt ijtimāʻīyah min tārīkh al-ʻIrāq al-ḥadīth / Social aspects of Iraqi modern history. Vol. 4: Min ʻām 1914 ilá ʻām 1918 -- al-juzʼ (Baghdād: Maṭbaʻat al-Shaʻab, 1974).
    OCLC: 14977769. Aleph BSN: 7944560.
  - Wardī, ʻAlī. Lamaḥāt ijtimāʻīyah min tārīkh al-ʻIrāq al-ḥadīth / Social aspects of Iraqi modern history. Vol. 6: Min ʻām 1920 ilá ʻām 1924. (Baghdād: Maṭbaʻat al-Maʻārif, 1976).
  - Al-Zaīdī, Dr. Sanān Sādiq Hussein; and Al-Jābrī, Dr. Khalīl Hamoud Uthmān. Arkān 'Ibādī: āhd ruwwād bina' al-daulah al-'irāqīyah (no publisher, no location, 2014).
    Inscription by author on title page, to Adnan Pachachi, January 2015. Aleph BSN: 7974414.
  - Zakī, Maʼmūn Amīn. Izdihār al-ʻIrāq taḥta al-ḥukm al-Mulukī, 1921-1958 :dirāsah tārīkhīyah, siyāsīyah, ijtimāʻīyah muqāranah (London: Dār al-Ḥikmah, 2011)
    Inscribed by author on title page, to Adnan Pachachi, 2011. ISBN: 190492378X. OCLC: 712592754. Aleph BSN: 7944553
  - Zaki, Saniha Amin, edited by Ellen Jawdat. Memoir of an Iraqi woman doctor [Place of publication not identified, 2014]
    Inscribed on title page by author, to Adnan Pachachi, 2015. ISBN: 9781501077982. OCLC: 931570398. Aleph BSN: 7944542
  - Zuhdī, Zāhid Muḥammad. al-Jawāhirī: ṣannājat al-shiʻr al-ʻArabī fī al-qarn al-ʻishrīn (Beirut: Dār al Qalam, 1999).
    Inscribed by author on flyleaf, to Adnan Pachachi, in Abu Dhabi, January 2000. OCLC: 43544051. Aleph BSN: 7974409.
- United Arab Emirates titles, 1978-2014
  - ʻAbd Allāh, Muḥammad Mursī. The United Arab Emirates: a modern history (London: Croom Helm, 1978)
    Inscription on flyleaf to Adnan Pachachi, 1978. ISBN: 0064949982. OCLC: 4099463. Aleph BSN: 002551547
  - Current transformations and their potential role in realizing change in the Arab world. (Abu Dhabi: Emirates Center for Strategic Studies and Research, 2007.)
    Contains paper by Adnan Pachachi, "Iraq as a Model for the Spread of Democracy in the Arab World," pages 59-64. ISBN: 9789948008743. Aleph BSN: 548259
  - Dhihlī, Ibrāhīm. Abū Ẓaby: dhikrayā̄t min al-māḍī (Dawlat al-Imārāt al-ʻArabīyah al-Muttaḥidah: Kuttāb Publishing, 2014)
    Inscribed by author on flyleaf, to Adnan Pachachi, March 2015. ISBN: 9789948225959. OCLC: 936496626. Aleph BSN: 4130783.
  - Fares, Mohammed Fares. Zāyid fī al-wathā'iq al-Barītānīyah (Abu Dhabi: al-Majlis al-Watani al-'Ulum, 2008)
    Inscribed by author on flyleaf, to Adnan Pachachi, January 2008. ISBN: 9789948036029. OCLC: 798389753. Aleph BSN: 7944560.
  - Ḥanẓal, Fāliḥ. al-Mufaṣṣal fī tārīkh al-Imārāt al-ʻArabīyah al-Muttaḥidah ([Abū Ẓaby]: al-Imārāt al-ʻArabīyah al-Muttaḥidah, Lajnat al-Turāth wa-al-Tārīkh, 1983).
    Inscription from author on flyleaf, to Adnan Pachachi, January 1984. OCLC: 12105795. Aleph BSN: 7974415.
  - Ḥammūdī, Najm al-Dīn ʻAbd Allāh. Qiyām Dawlat al-Imārāt al-ʻArabīyah al-Muttaḥidah: mudhakkirāt wa-dirāsāt (Abu Dhabi: [ʻAbd Allāh Najm al-Dīn ʻAbd Allāh Ḥammudī], 2014)
    ISBN: 9948851021. OCLC: 62151318. Aleph BSN: 7994556.
  - Holton, Patricia. Mother without a mask: a Westerner's story of her Arab family (London: Motivate Pub., 1991)
    ISBN: 1873544251. OCLC: 123766276. Aleph BSN: 7944546.
  - Khalifa wa al-ta'alun al-duwali: sahib al-sheikh Khalifa bin Zayed al- Nahyyan, ra'is daulah al-Emarat...(Abu Dhabi: Maktab na'ib ra'is majlis al-wizara' li-shu'un al-'ilam, 2004).
    Aleph BSN: 7974412.
  - Khalis, Dr. Walid Hamoud. Fadl al-'Arab wa-al-tanbīh 'alā 'ulūmihā (Abu Dhabi: Cultural Foundation, 1998)
    Inscribed by author on flyleaf, to Adnan Pachachi, March 2002. OCLC: 727126978, BSN: 1652912
  - Khalis, Dr. Walid Hamoud. Sheikh Zayed bin Sultan al Nahyan: dirasat fi 'anasir al'abda' al-sh'ari [Sheikh Zayed...a study in the elements of poetic creativity] (Oman: Sultan Qaboos University, 2002)
    Inscribed by author on title page, to Adnan Pachachi, in Abu Dhabi, January 2003. BSN: 7974416
  - Nahyan, Khalid S. Z. The three islands: mapping the UAE-Iran dispute. (London: Royal United Services Institute, 2013)
    ISBN: 0855261043. OCLC: 870345262. Aleph BSN: 3932730.
  - Rashid, Noor Ali. Sheikh Zayed, life and times: through the lens of Noor Ali Rashid (Dubai, UAE: Motivate Pub., 2001).
    ISBN: 186063124X. OCLC: 51269718. Aleph BSN: 7944550.
- General, 1911-2003
  - British Petroleum Company. Our industry, petroleum: petroleum: a handbook dealing with the organisation and functions of an integrated international oil company, with particular reference to the British Petroleum Company Limited. 4th edition. (London, 1970)
    Aleph BSN: 7944545.
  - Cottrell, Alvin J. The Persian Gulf States: a general survey (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1980)
    Inscription from author, on flyleaf, to Dr. Adel al-Haimus, Washington, DC, January 1983. ISBN: 0801822041. OCLC: 5310646. Aleph BSN:002571263.
  - Damlūjī, Fārūq. Tārīkh al-adyān: al-ulūhīyah wa-tārīkh al-ālihah (Bayrūt: al-Ahlīyah, 2003)
    Inscribed by author on flyleaf, to Adnan Pachachi, 2002. OCLC: 57712426. Aleph BSN: 7944562
  - Hourani, George Fadlo. Arab seafaring in the Indian Ocean in ancient and early medieval times. (Beirut: Khayats, 1963)
    OCLC: 1914243. Aleph BSN: 7944548.
  - Jawdat, Nameer Ali, editor. Selected documents of the international petroleum industry 1967 (Vienna: [Information Dept.] Organization of the Petroleum Exporting Countries, 1968)
    OCLC: 7079236. Aleph BSN: 7944547.
  - Khalid bin Sultan, Prince, with Patrick Seale. Desert warrior: a personal view of the Gulf War by the Joint Forces commander (New York: HarperCollins Publishers, 1995).
    ISBN: 0060172983. OCLC: 32576544. Aleph BSN: 7944551.
  - Khalis, Dr. Walid Hamoud. al-Shuʻarāʼ al-nuqqād. (Kuwait: Maktaba al Falah, 1986)
    Inscribed by author on title page, to Adnan Pachachi, June 1986. OCLC: 23531305, BSN: 7944563.
  - Memorandum and articles of association of Turkish Petroleum Company, Limited (London: Bischoff, Coxe, Bishoff and Thompson, 1911)
    Note: Privately bound compilation of articles of incorporation of TPC, with other resolutions bound with it, and typescript Arabic translations of same. Aleph BSN: 7944552.